<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fairest fairing for a schoole-bred sonne whereby praise, ease, and profit may be wonne : that is to say, The schoole- masters precepts, or, Lillies lesson to his schollers, teaching them good manners / translated by Iohn Penkethman louer of learning, and by him dedicated to all the laureat Lillies of these times.</title>
            <title>Carmen de moribus. English. 1630</title>
            <author>Lily, William, 1468?-1522.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19598.6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4816</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23919043</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23919043</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26981</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09284)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26981)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1838:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fairest fairing for a schoole-bred sonne whereby praise, ease, and profit may be wonne : that is to say, The schoole- masters precepts, or, Lillies lesson to his schollers, teaching them good manners / translated by Iohn Penkethman louer of learning, and by him dedicated to all the laureat Lillies of these times.</title>
                  <title>Carmen de moribus. English. 1630</title>
                  <author>Lily, William, 1468?-1522.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1630]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Translation of Lily's Carmen de moribus--Cf. STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Caption title over [2] p.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>School children --  England --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:26981:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:26981:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <head>
               <l>The faireſt Fairing for a Schoole-bred Sonne;</l>
               <l>Whereby Praiſe, Eaſe, and Profit may be wonne.</l>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>That is to ſay,</hi>
               <lb/> 
The Schoole-Maſters precepts, or <hi>Lillies</hi> Leſſon to his Schollers.
teaching them good Manners.</head>
            <byline>Tranſlated by <hi>Iohn Penkethman</hi> Louer of Learning; and by him Dedicated to all the laureat LILLIES of theſe times.</byline>
            <argument>
               <p>This Table may be cut a croſſe betweene the two middle lines, and inſerted in the Grammar.</p>
            </argument>
            <l>MY little Scholler, to thy Booke inclinde,</l>
            <l>Come neere, and print my Sayings in thy minde;</l>
            <l>Leaue thy Bed early, let not Sleepe inuade thee;</l>
            <l>Haſte thee to Church and worſhip him that made thee:</l>
            <l>Yet firſt thy Hands and Viſage waſh thou faire,</l>
            <l>Let all thy Clothes be neat, and combe thy Haire;</l>
            <l>And when my Schoole ſhall bid thee come away,</l>
            <l>Be there without excuſe of loytring Stay:</l>
            <l>When there thou ſeeſt thy Maſter, him ſalute,</l>
            <l>And to thy Mates in order be not mute:</l>
            <l>Sit where I ſet thee, and in any caſe,</l>
            <l>Vnleſſe I countermand it, keepe thy place;</l>
            <l>And as more Learning euerie one doth get,</l>
            <l>So in a higher place he ſhall be ſet:</l>
            <l>And for thy Studies haue thou ready ſtill,</l>
            <l>MY little Scholler, to thy Booke inclinde,</l>
            <l>Come neere, and print my Sayings in thy minde;</l>
            <l>Leaue thy Bed early, let not Sleepe inuade thee;</l>
            <l>Haſte thee to Church and worſhip him that made thee:</l>
            <l>Yet firſt thy Hands and Viſage waſh thou faire,</l>
            <l>Let all thy Clothes be neat, and combe thy Haire;</l>
            <l>And when my Schoole ſhall bid thee come away,</l>
            <l>Be there without excuſe of loytring Stay:</l>
            <l>When there thou ſeeſt thy Maſter, him ſalute,</l>
            <l>And to thy Mates in order be not mute:</l>
            <l>Sit where I ſet thee, and in any caſe,</l>
            <l>Vnleſſe I countermand it, keepe thy place;</l>
            <l>And as more Learning euerie one doth get,</l>
            <l>So in a higher place he ſhall be ſet:</l>
            <l>And for thy Studies haue thou ready ſtill,</l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 line">
                  <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>If ought to thee I dictate or allot,</l>
            <l>Write thou it rightly, without fault or ſpot;</l>
            <l>But ſuch thy writings doe thou not commit</l>
            <l>To papers looſe, for which a Booke is fit.</l>
            <l>Record thy Leſſons more than once or twice,</l>
            <l>And if thou doubt'ſt, of Others aske aduiſe:</l>
            <l>Who doubts and often askes, my charge retaineth,</l>
            <l>But he that nothing doubts, no profit gaineth.</l>
            <l>Learne, Boy, nor let Forgetfulneſſe abuſe thee,</l>
            <l>Leſt that a guiltie minde of Sloth accuſe thee.</l>
            <l>And marke me well, for what auaile my paines,</l>
            <l>Vnleſſe thou fix my Sayings in thy Braines:</l>
            <l>"The hardeſt things through diligence are knowne;</l>
            <l>Be painefull, and the Glorie is thine owne.</l>
            <l>"For as the Earth yeilds neither ſeeds nor flowers,</l>
            <l>"Unleſſe man<gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r'd in <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:26981:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
"So he that doth not exercize his wit</l>
            <l>"Doth loſe, with precious time, the hope of it.</l>
            <l>Let Order likewiſe in thy ſpeech commend thee,</l>
            <l>Leſt by vnciuill Babbling thou offend me;</l>
            <l>Speake lowe, when thou thy Leſſon doſt apply,</l>
            <l>But to Mee ſaying, let thy voice be high.</l>
            <l>To Mee, when thou repeat'ſt, <hi>ad vnguem,</hi> looke</l>
            <l>Thou haſt all readie, laying by thy booke.</l>
            <l>And let None prompt thee, when thou art repeating,</l>
            <l>For that much hurts thee, and deſcrues a Beating.</l>
            <l>If ought I queſtion, anſwer ſo the ſame,</l>
            <l>As thou thereby mayſt merit praiſe and fame.</l>
            <l>No praiſe thou get'ſt in ſpeech to runne or creepe,</l>
            <l>"The Meane's a Vertue profiting to keepe;</l>
            <l>And euer when thou ſpeak'ſt vſe Latine phraſe,</l>
            <l>Yet ſhun thou barbarous words as rockie wayes;</l>
            <l>Inſtructions askt vnto thy fellowes grant;</l>
            <l>And helpe (to my deſire) the Ignorant:</l>
            <l>"Thoſe that want Learning, he that ſeekes to teach,</l>
            <l>"Himſelfe (though moſt vnlearn'd) may all outreach.</l>
            <l>But let no paultrie Maſters giue thee aime,</l>
            <l>To Romane Eloquence no little ſhame;</l>
            <l>'Mongſt whom there's none ſo fooliſh, or ſo rude,</l>
            <l>But him an Author the like Sort conclude.</l>
            <l>The Grammar Lawes if thou wouldſt rightly knowe,</l>
            <l>And learne to make thy Speech more ſweetly flowe,</l>
            <l>Read workes moſt famous by old Authors wrought,</l>
            <l>And which the chiefeſt Latiniſts haue taught;</l>
            <l>Now <hi>Virgil,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Terence</hi> doth inuite thee,</l>
            <l>And otherwhiles would <hi>Cicero</hi> delight thee;</l>
            <l>All which who learnes not, onely dreames doth ſee,</l>
            <l>And in Cimmerian ſhades would euer bee.</l>
            <l>Some Boyes, (their mindes denying Vertue roome)</l>
            <l>The time doe loue in Trifles to conſume:</l>
            <l>Others, their Fellowes trouble, making ſport</l>
            <l>With hands or feet, or in ſome other ſort.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:26981:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
And Thoſe there are that boaſting of their ſtocks,</l>
            <l>Diſparage Others with vnſauourie mocks:</l>
            <l>Such euill patterns doe not thou regard,</l>
            <l>Leſt that thy deeds at length haue iuſt reward:</l>
            <l>Nor buy, nor ſell, nor changing giue or take;</l>
            <l>By others Loſſe doe thou no profit make:</l>
            <l>Let money goe, which many hath defilde.</l>
            <l>"Nothing, but what is chaſte becomes a childe;</l>
            <l>Doe not lye, ſteale, ſcoffe, brabble, fight, or iarre,</l>
            <l>Ill noyſe and ſcornefull laughter baniſh farre.</l>
            <l>To no diſhoneſt words enure thy breath,</l>
            <l>"Mans Tongue the Portall is of life and death.</l>
            <l>Hold it a heynous crime, moſt worthy blame,</l>
            <l>To raile, or ſweare by Gods moſt holy Name.</l>
            <l>Keepe ſafe thy Bookes, (not leauing one at Schoole)</l>
            <l>With all things elſe, which is a ſpeciall Rule.</l>
            <l>Yea flie what ere may cauſe thee to offend</l>
            <l>Me, or the meaneſt One: and ſo I end.</l>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Tranſlators Concluſion to the Schollers.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THeſe Precepts who performe, their Maſter pleaſe;</l>
                  <l>And reape thereby both profit, praiſe and eaſe:</l>
                  <l>But Thoſe that breake the leaſt, his Anger gaine,</l>
                  <l>Working their owne loſſe with reproach and paine.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>To the Parents.</head>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <l>Et iſti haec rejicere malè nolunt</l>
                  <l>Qui filijs &amp; <hi>Qui mihi</hi> benè volunt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>That is,</p>
               <q xml:lang="eng">
                  <l>And Thoſe will not vnkindely Theſe reiect,</l>
                  <l>That honeſt Precepts and their Sonnes affect.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
